These rounds of layoffs are happening.
The next round is likely coming very
shortly. This is Asian Dad Energy, the
anonymous big techie who got laid off
after 25 years in tech, and I
interviewed him about that experience.
>> It was anxiety, panic, excitement,
everything.
>> We also talked about his early career in
engineering consulting. How does that
software not explode when you hand it
off to the customer? It's your
obligation to tell your client that,
hey, the $20 million that you've
invested is a steaming pile of turds.
>> We covered his transition into big tech
and much more.
>> The compensation of big tech is bonkers,
more than double, closer to tripling.
You mentioned that people should expect
future layoffs. What makes you think
that?
Here's the full episode.
I wanted to start by asking you a little
bit about the layoff story. I think it's
that first video that you did that kind
of went very viral and I wanted to hear
a little bit about what was going on at
the time and what were the the
conversations like in the layoff. I was
working for this big tech company,
right? And like a lot of big tech
companies, we already had multiple
rounds of layoffs. Um and in this
particular round there were there were
rumors ahead of time that it was coming
and everyone sort of knew that it was
coming. What was up in the air was sort
of like which business units and
business lines are affected and how many
folks are going to get cut. Um, I think
it's probably because of either sort of
my seniority within the organization or
the relationship networks that had
cultivated. I sort of got heads up about
sort of like the nature of this layoff.
Um, I also had a heads up that I was on
the list uh to be to be cut. And so
essentially I knew these two things were
happening. I had some other sort of life
experiences and thoughts at that time
that sort of made me question a little
bit about why I was working in big tech
in the first place. There were many sort
of things. I kind of described them in
detail in my vlog. Um but at that point
I then found out through the grapevines
that a couple of more junior engineers
are also on this particular wave to be
cut. Um and so what I essentially did
was I was able to do a little switcheroo
where I put myself to the top of the
list and got cut and that's how I got
laid off. Um, now obviously and this is
this is just me conjecturing at this
point since I'm no longer with the
company, these rounds of layoffs are
happening. The next round is likely
coming very shortly if not already upon
us. So, it seems for me the best I did
was I just bought these guys a little
bit of time, a mere matter of months.
Hopefully, they use the time wisely. Um,
that's the best I could do. What was the
reason for this layoff?
>> It's only a conjecture on my side and I
think it's not just affecting sort of my
ex employer, but maybe many big tech and
tech companies.
We're sort of like right now in this
race, right, to to demonstrate the value
of AI.
And I'm not saying AI has no value, but
there is a lot of pressure to
essentially demonstrate value for all
the investments that companies have been
putting into AI. And one of those ways
to do that is to decrease headcount.
Because if you're able to decrease
headcount, your product lines are still
being sold. So at least temporarily your
revenue as a company is not affected but
your cost has just gone down a lot
because you decreased your headcount.
That along with good marketing talking
about efficiencies gained through AI can
really drive up your company's stock
valuation. So, at least to me, I feel
like we're sort of like in this meta,
right, where companies are looking to
decrease headcount, reduce their cost,
keep the revenue consistent, and then
get some PR points for saying how
innovative they are in terms of the AI
revolution.
>> When you heard that um you were on the
list and you were kind of getting that
warning, what was going through your
head?
>> It was weird, man. It was it was
anxiety,
panic,
excitement,
like fear, hope,
everything. Cuz I felt like I was in
this this thing where I was doing the
same thing for at that point years. And
this was a sudden change, right? I
didn't know if it was a good change or a
bad change, but it was a major change
that's coming to my life. And so it was
this cocktail of emotions that that I
was feeling very very unstable a very
unstable kind of mentality that I had
there for a couple of days.
>> Were you presented severance at that
point or how does that whole process
work? So with with my ex employer, it
was a very structured process and
they're a very good employer in the
sense that they will make the the grant
the sort of they will reveal the broad
outlines of how your exit will look
like, right? They'll they'll put you
onto the sort of garden leave where
you're still with the company for a
period of time, but you can apply for
jobs. Generally, they'll give you a
pretty
they'll give you a fairly generous
severance and they'll also give you
other things, right? Like for example,
if you have any vacation days that would
be or PTO days that would be paid out,
right? Um there's usually a stipend of
some sort for education or for equipment
and so on and so forth. And they sort of
clearly articulate that ahead of time.
And so if one does the math right, it's
actually a very generous package that
you end up getting because you're you're
getting months of garden leave, you're
getting months of severance, you're
getting a stipen, you're getting all of
your PTO's for like a whole year. And so
so it it was very it was very clear. It
was very transparent and uh it was well
timed.
>> Was this something that's negotiable? I
I think anything is negotiable
um technically, right? But really, I
just wasn't in the right mental state to
think about negotiating for it. I kind
of it kind of this whole thing sort of
made me pause and just reflect on life
and what I've been doing this whole time
with my life. And so the the last thing
I really cared about is like, hey, let
me let me negotiate for an extra 20% on
this severance package. That really was
on the bottom of my list of priorities.
You mentioned that people should expect
future layoffs. What makes you think
that?
>> So when I was saying that, I was
thinking more of the tech industry,
right? The big tech companies and other
sort of ancillary tech companies. The
reason why I have this feeling is
because it seems like the entire sector
has invested greatly in the last couple
of years definitely into AI and there
almost feels to me like there's a kind
of overinvestment that's brewing in
there where a lot of companies are
essentially putting AI into every
possible feature of every possible
product and platform and service and all
of those investments are not yielding
clear returns. And so I just sort of
have this feeling that whether the
company would lay off to sort of
decrease cost and performatively show
their AI efficiency or lay off because
they're running short on money or lay
off because they really have to lay off
because their business lines are
collapsing. It just seems like there's a
there's this meta trend towards shedding
tech employees from from these companies
because of years of overinvestment and
not enough returns for the investment
given. That's just the feeling that I
have and it could be totally wrong,
right? I could be completely wrong but
it's my current feeling giving the whole
vibe of this entire sector.
>> Right? So I I could see that direction.
And on the flip side, things could be
very positive. Maybe AI could empower
people. Maybe the revenue per person
goes up a lot. And we realize we want
more people or something like that.
These people are really worth their
their labor is worth more. We want more
people working on more things. Possible
as well, right?
>> It is absolutely possible for that to
happen. Right. the future to me the
future is unwritten. So it's entirely
possible that hey we do see the
productivity gains of all these AI
investments and the value of these tech
companies literally shoot to the moon. I
would actually very much hope for that
um because all all of my a lot of my
investments and stocks and so on are
with these companies. So if they go to
the moon I would be happy as a clam at
this point. Um, it though feels to me
that the what I just described
at least to me seems higher probability
than this sort of like happy future
probability.
>> You've had 25 years in the industry.
Your career grew throughout the ranks of
the various companies that you were at.
So, I kind of want to go over, you know,
looking back on your career. What are
the things that you learned? What are
the things that you wish you would have
changed? if you could just lay out your
career from the beginning just on a high
level and then maybe we can talk about
different pieces of it and and uh see
what people could learn.
>> So I I got into tech early on into
computer programming in high school. Um
in college I majored in computer science
and I started doing these little side
projects and consulting gigs for various
small companies in college. Um coming
out of college, I joined a a digital
consulting company like a consulting
agency and I spent many years in the
sort of consulting agency space and I
sort of went through the the range of
roles that a uh software engineer can go
through, right? So you start as a junior
software engineer, you graduate to being
a senior developer or a senior software
engineer, then you move on to becoming
kind of like a tech lead of a
development squad. Then the progression
goes towards the architect level where
you become an application architect, an
enterprise architect, a senior
enterprise architect all the way through
the director levels right of being a
technical director. Um then uh for me I
made the decision uh after much
reflection of leaving the consulting
space and entering and joining a big
tech company. And upon joining the big
tech company sort of I I I went into
this whole kind of senior enterprise
architect chief architect role where
you're essentially overseeing
architecture across the entire ecosystem
of applications and platforms and I did
that for the last several years before
my layoff. What's the nature of the work
when you do uh software engineering
consulting? Is it you're part of a firm
that has software engineering expertise
and then there are other firms that
don't have that expertise that want
features built and then you guys deploy
a team to help for a limited amount of
time to build something and then
>> so the consulting space works like this
your consulting company has different
sort of skills right maybe it's
different types of software engineering
maybe it's building a CMS maybe it's
creating e-commerce sites maybe it's
middleware and backend integration Maybe
it's digital transformation and you have
clients that are usually other
companies, right? Sometimes they're
small companies, a lot of times they're
big Fortune 500 companies and you're
essentially then inserted into these
clients to rapidly build out the systems
for them. And that involves usually
working with the clients themselves,
their IT and technology teams and
departments as well as other vendors,
other consulting and service companies.
A lot of times it's a very dynamic maybe
chaotic system where you sort of have to
find your place, survive in this
ecosystem where where you're one actor
in a range of actors, build the thing to
the best of your abilities, and then you
ship out to the next project. And uh
it's a very fast-paced environment. It's
a very kind of like learn as you go
environment from my experience. And it
was a very good one that I enjoyed
doing. One thing with that model that's
just a media thing that comes to my mind
is a large part of software engineering
is maintaining software and making sure
it stays up, it's high quality. When
things change around the software, we
make sure that we patch bugs and various
things like that. So if you were to just
build something and then pass it to
another company, how does that software
remain useful and not explode when you
hand it off to the customer? It's it's a
great question. There's sort of two
answers to this question, right? There
is the hey get in, build, and get out
model, right? And I've seen my fair
share of such projects. There's also the
retainer model where your consulting
agency works with a client for a long
period of time, sometimes years um and
you sort of not only build it but you
maintain the software and you enhance
and build additional features and
extensions to the software. I have seen
and worked with this model as well. The
general case is when you have a
retainer, you have the time of really
knowing the codebase and especially if
you built the platform from the ground
up, there's this institutional knowledge
of how do you maintain it and how do you
enhance it and those are the kind of
better types of projects um as a
consultant. But the other kind of
project is more like fly by night,
right? where you got to as a company
have a pipeline of work, right, to keep
all your consultants employed. And so
sometimes you would sell in a project
purely for monetary means. And
unfortunately, a lot of companies, a lot
of agencies and consulting companies do
this in the economy. And so what you'll
sometimes have is as an architect, for
example, you go to a client, you'll see
this ecosystem that's literally this
dizzying patchwork of platforms and
sites and systems that are a lot of
times redundant and a lot of times
incompatible because of all of these
vendors and agencies and IT services
companies doing their thing. And it sort
of almost like becomes this dumpster
fire that especially if you're hired as
a consultant to do a digital
transformation, you sort of have to put
out the fire and kind of stitch
everything together just to have a
working platform for your client. So
I've seen both and both are are kind of
fun and anxietyinducing in their own
ways. In my experience in in building
stuff, a lot of the times we build
software, it's just within consistent
teams where you see that person every
day. As a consultant, you you come in,
you're dropped, you're parachuted into
some other team. What is the default
culture like or what's that that
experience like?
>> So, in my experience, I've encountered
all of those scenarios. It depends
completely on the clients. Some clients
have rigid hierarchical cultures. Some
clients have much more open and
cooperative cultures. Some clients have
the sort of internal startup model where
literally you're part of an internal
startup. And so that entire range of
different kind of environments could
happen as a comp consultant when you're
dropped in. Part of your skill as a
consultant, right, is not just knowing
the tech and being able to architect and
being able to bang out code. It is to
understand the topology of the client
political environment. How does the
client teams interact with each other?
How do they interact with other
consulting agencies or IT services
agencies in this ecosystem? And as you
sort of progress in your career as a
consultant, eventually it becomes part
of your your job almost to be able to
navigate and open up a space for your
consulting agency within this client
ecosystem. And you keep the book of
orders going, right, with additional
work and and uh stuff. For me, the early
rungs of this was highly enjoyable,
right? that the learning of these new
cultures and environments and new
technical ecosystems and then adapting
and improving these it was highly highly
enjoyable near the sort of the the
latter portion of my consulting career
it kind of shifted the work that I was
doing shifted as I became more and more
senior so instead of being more of a
hands-on hey let's design this quilt of
systems based on these components that
you guys have it became more of like hey
drop me off at the sea suite and let me
sell this vision of digital
transformation to the CMO or the CSO or
the CEO of this Fortune 500 corporation.
Um I did that for a couple of years the
last couple of years as a consultant and
uh I I sort of I sort of got a little
burnt out by it.
>> What burnt you out? the gap between the
ideal that I was selling and the
actuality of what was actually there,
right? Because the actuality, the
sausage making is dirty. It is chaotic.
You have systems that don't talk to each
other. You have code bases that hasn't
been maintained for 5 years, right? You
have different teams. You have like
offshore vendors who sometimes can't
even communicate with onshore teams,
right? But but that is not the vision.
that is sold to the executives in the
seauite, right? You know what the vision
is? The vision of a digital
transformation is usually like this
smooth diagram where you capture
customer insights. You have this bubble
that does a rationale and a decision is
made and immediately sales and orders
come in and revenue goes up. That's the
dream that's sold. Now compare that with
the actuality. If you're the person that
needs to make those two things come
together and happen, which I was
eventually as a as a group technical
director, it just gets too much. Is
there any feedback mechanism? Let's say
you you sell this vision and their
company says, "We love it. Transform us
digitally. This sounds amazing." and
then you come in and you build a
steaming
broken code base that just kind of works
but not really. Do you would you still
get paid as a consulting company? So
this may be a timed dependent question
right because I feel that there was a
period of time around the 2010s where
every company was talking about digital
transformation. This this is the era of
companies going from like spreadsheets
and printouts to like mobile apps and
sites and you know essentially having a
fully digital experience for their
customer. At that point the honest
question is a lot of the times the
decision makers the executives the
seauite they're not fully aware of the
sausage making that happens under the
hood like all of these all of these
ridiculous duct tape implementations and
like swivel chair operations with people
workarounds for APIs that doesn't work
and breaks all of those details are sort
of obuse cated at that level. But what
they see is like, oh my goodness, a
customer can go through this web mobile
app and they get a text message telling
them that their order is delivered and
line goes up.
If you're able to do that as a
consultant, you're going to get paid.
And so from from my experience, it was
overwhelmingly positive that that it's
hard in the initial stages to get a
digital transformation wrong cuz all
you're doing is taking something that
happens in the analog world that used to
happen in the analog world and making it
digital. Maybe it's not the best
implementation, but essentially you're
going from zero to one.
I see. Yeah, I could see that. um
exploding on them later if there's some
issue something like that. Well, one
thing I I could see here is these these
uh seauite people they're non-technical
in a majority of cases I'm assuming and
so they probably don't have the judgment
to know what good work looks like in
this domain. And so I kind of see a
natural information asymmetry here. What
stops the technical consultant from
coming in and saying it's great and then
but it's actually very far from great.
You you have to have you have to have
sort of like your own personal
boundaries as a technologist, right? And
as an engineer, you're you're taught or
I hope all of us as engineers are taught
that there's sort of like engineering
integrity. And it's really funny because
when I was in university, there
literally was a course on this, right?
Like you you have to have respect for
the truth, for quality, and for
integrity of what you're building. And
that that is kind of critical. I I hope
to God that I have followed this
throughout my career as a consultant. I
tried my very best to do it. Right? If
it is a steaming pile of turds, it's
your obligation to tell your client
that, "Hey, hey, man, like the the $20
million that you've invested is a
steaming pile of turds." That's what
you're supposed to do. Are there
consultants who didn't do that? I'm
sure. I'm sure. But we tried our best to
do so.
>> I I was trying to think what is the
what's the incentive structure that
could prevent that? And I guess it would
be probably the reputation of the
consulting firm, which is if you deliver
that steaming pile to customer one,
you're not going to get customer two or
three or anything like that.
>> Correct. That is a that is something
that could happen, right? But just in
general, and it may be something with a
person's career, right? I went through
this phase in my career where where I
was obsessed with sort of the quality
and and longevity of the software that I
was building. I don't know if in your
development career if you went through
the same thing, but this this striving
for excellence, for efficiency to
sometimes it can get totally OCD like
you'd be like, "Oh, this piece of code
here is not performant enough. We're
going to optimize the heck out of it to
do this thing perfectly." But there is
that part of a person's career where you
really are obsessing about the quality
of what you build and you sort of almost
take like the quality of your end
product as a personal reflection upon
yourself. So if you if you build a
steaming pile of turds, you're going to
feel ashamed about Yeah, definitely.
Well, I mean when I think to big tech or
from my experience and I think what is
the incentive structure that makes it so
that we put out quality work is that we
have technical leaders who are
controlling the performance incentives.
So people who get promoted they often
build things that are ideally performant
or the metrics that matter are improving
and the way that they're done is high
quality. So they are operationally
excellent. The implementation quality is
something where it's not going to break
in the future and we kind of prevent uh
a lot of a large class of bugs from
happening just in the way that it's
implemented. And but the like the key
takeaway there is the leaders
themselves, the people who control the
incentives of the engineers, they're
technical and there's this whole system
that's set up that says, "Hey, if you if
you do good work, you get rewarded."
good as deemed by technical people. So
the thing that's interesting to me here
is the people who say this is good it
the in other words the client they're
not technical. So, I would have thought
you could deliver the thing that's not
operationally excellent or the thing
that's not particularly well done as
long as the inputs and outputs are
acceptable, ship it off and disappear
because you don't necessarily have uh as
much skin in the game as the client
does.
>> Ryan, you you could do that. But in my
experience, right, and that's not only
as a software engineer that's sort of
climbing or going up the ranks from my
mentors and leaders at the time, but
also my experience at the director and
above level where I was in those sort of
leadership roles, right? That that the
[clears throat] the pride and the care
for the work and the quality of that
work was very high. you you really do
have a significant number of people that
kind of cares a lot about the quality of
their software that they're building and
the systems that they're building. That
that's sort of one thing and it's a
human element to it, but I think it's an
important one because if you don't have
that quality, nothing stops us from
delivering just crap to the clients,
right? And as you pointed out yourself,
you can only do that so many times
before the reputation of a firm of a
consulting agency is ruined. And nobody
wants that.
>> Yeah, definitely. I guess it's you could
make the same analogies which the
leadership at the consulting company
could say, hey, you get promoted to a
higher level as a engineering consultant
if you build good things and they review
the the things that are built. And um
yeah, I I could see that happening as
well. One last thing that I wanted to go
over on the consulting side is and I
don't know a whole lot about consulting,
but I feel like I see in pop culture or
in various interviews or jokes that you
know consultants are it's a job that a
lot of people they don't they say ah we
don't want consultants here some
something like that. What is the reason
that that people say consulting is not a
good thing? So sometimes I've observed
right when being dropped onto a client's
side that there is sort of hesitation
and resistance
and in my experience a lot of that
actually comes from management
consulting rather than technical
consulting in the sense that sometimes
it feels like management consulting sort
sort of like any any business that
you're running right you have people
process and tools
Right. Fundamentally technical
consulting deals with the tools and it
may deal with the process to a to a
smaller extent but the people portion of
it is usually management consulting and
that sometimes leads to decisions that
has an adverse impact on people working
in these client companies. Right? So
management consultants may for example
take a look at all of the teams working
on your business and decides that x% of
these teams are redundant. They don't
they're they're they're not needed. And
a lot of times the clients would be
influenced to do things like lay off x
percentage of people. And so if that
happens enough times there then is the
impression that hey a consulting team is
coming. Oh my goodness our jobs are are
at risk and we're going to get laid off.
And at least to me that feels like the
majority of where that sort of vibes
come in. From my personal experience,
people are going to be people and most
people are nice. And so if you drop you
get dropped to a client side and you
work with them, you get to know them,
90% of times they're great guys. You you
mentioned around seven years ago or so
you transitioned from this consulting
space to working in big tech. What was
that transition like? Okay. So at that
point pretty much all I did as a
consultant was get shipped to a
boardroom and sell digital
transformation to a seauite.
All right. So I was in a I was terribly
bored of that role. It just felt like
I'm further and further disconnected
from the actual implementation that I
cut my teeth on as a young man. So a
good colleague of mine had become an
executive at this big tech company and
so he introduced me to this particular
role. Um it was a hands-on role as a
chief architect. Right on paper you're
essentially working on design of
applications across an ecosystem. And in
practice, I found that when I when I
jumped in there that I had the ability
to, for example, deep dive on a specific
system and lead the buildout of
individual systems that were deemed
important by the organization. And that
then allowed me to do way more than work
on, you know, VO diagrams. I could
literally, for example, take a component
that was really, really difficult and
code it out and build it. I could go
into debug sessions with teams. I can
tweak configuration. I can participate
in launches into production of different
platforms and that was um for me a very
refreshing change.
>> I you also mentioned um I mean the
compensation was different on a
percentage basis. Was it a you know
major difference or how big of a change
are you talking about?
>> The the the the compensation of big tech
is bonkers. I I I just I have to I have
to say that consultants are paid well.
They're comfortably paid. But you go
from consult or at least from my
experience, you go from consulting to
big tech, it's like the compensation
more than double closer to tripling. And
it's because of the structure and the
nature of compensation at big tech,
right? There there's you have you have
bonuses both sign on and reoccurring. A
lot of times you're given this thing
called an RSU, right? Restricted stock
units. And these are essentially shares
of the big tech company. And those
shares are vested usually over a period
of time, right? Over three or four
years, you get a chunk of it each year.
And then there are these um these stock
option-like programs like the employee
stock uh participation programs where
where you're you're essentially allowed
to purchase greatly discounted tranches
of shares of of the company. Right. So,
so for me, I got all of these things.
So, I got the bonuses, I got the RSU, I
got the ESP. And what essentially
happened was imagine having a base
salary that's already significantly
higher than than a consulting salary.
But then you have all these shares and
for these shares if you were to hold on
to them and for me I did hold on to them
those shares then doubled and then
tripled in value and so so at that point
the compensation between my new role in
big tech and my old one in consulting
it's not comparable between the two.
>> You mentioned ESP. I think people might
be curious about that. Can you explain?
>> Sure. What it is is it's sort of like
the company gives you the right to
purchase their stocks with your um uh
post tax salary, right? But the purchase
occurs in such a way that you're
guaranteed a discount
that's you know for for me it was around
15% below the market price of the stock.
Okay. So imagine if the stock of this
company is $100, you're guaranteed to be
able to purchase it for $85.
So if you were to do that and acquire
these stock shares periodically, right,
and then you hold on to them, it's
almost like you're baking in this this
advantage. And then those stocks, if if
you look at the majority of big tech
companies over the last seven years, the
majority of them kind of ballooned in
value over the COVID years especially
and has increased many hundreds of
percent. And so what essentially
happened with this is if you take these
stocks and then you hold on to it, it
will double or triple or quadruple in
value. And that's what happened to me.
>> Is there anything that will stop you
from selling it immediately? in the ESP
is like could you just buy it at 85% of
the cost and sell it immediately for
100% of the value?
>> Yes. Yes, you can. It's not advisable.
It's not advisable to do that. And you
know, times could be different, right?
Like if you if you're in a period where
where you believe the value of the stock
is going to go to the moon, it's really
not advisable to sell it instantly. Um
but of course stock markets are
inherently unpredictable. Anything can
happen, right? But for me when I was
accumulating those stocks sort of like I
had this um well there was co right and
if you remember what happened in co
there was this huge push into digital
platforms across the entire population
of the United States. So for me in my in
my simple little brain is telling me,
hey wait, so everybody is forced to use
digital tools. They don't have a choice.
Oh, and we we make a lot of these
digital tools. Maybe I should hold on to
these stocks. I think they might go up.
And they did. But going forward, right,
we don't know if that's the case. So
good judgment has to be made, right?
Whether to hold or to sell.
What a lot of people do is they buy
index funds so that they have a little
more diversification instead of holding
uh particular stock. But I mean it
sounds like regardless of if you want to
hold your company's stock or not, if
your company's offering the ability to
purchase it at a discount,
it's an immediate superset at least to
just buy it and sell it into cash. And
now if you were
>> they're giving you money. If someone's
just giving you money for nothing, you
should accept that money.
>> Well, what's the I don't get the what's
the incentive for them? Because if
there's no reason to hold I could see it
as a good way to keep people invested in
the company. If they said, "Hey, you can
buy at a discount, but you have to hold
on to it." Then yeah, maybe you buy it
and you say, "Do I want to take that
risk or do I believe?" But if you could
just buy it and I just buy it and sell
and put in cash or whatever the thing
was that I would have invested the money
in otherwise. So it's it's interesting.
It's an interesting perk. I would
totally if my company had it, I would
use ESPPS like crazy. It's one of those
things that you sort of it kind of makes
you stop and think about it a little
bit. And I was sort of two minds. There
was a part of me that wanted to sell it
and there was a part of me that wanted
to hold it. I think what just sort of
made the decision for me was for much of
my time in big tech, it was during
COVID, right? And during those COVID
years, you could sort of see the
explosive growth. And so for me, it was
a sort of a light bulb boom of like,
wait, this might last for a while. Maybe
I'll just I'll just hold on for dear
life since it seems to be going to the
moon. That's it. At that time, if I had
given you $10,000 of cash, would you
have turned around and bought your
company's stock or would you have put it
somewhere else? For me, it would have
been index funds just because I'm I'm
I'm sort of a risk adverse guy and so if
there was just cash in my hands, sure,
I'll put into index funds because I see
the ESGP. It sounds like it has the
flexibility of being cash if you want. I
guess maybe there's some tax implication
when you sell it.
>> I I don't know. I didn't research too
much into this, right? I'm not I'm not
like a financial guru or anything, but
it's sort of like, you know, if if you
get money for free, you should you
should take that money. Um there there's
there's of course other things, right?
Like I think a lot of companies will
give you like a 401k match as well. Um
you should take that as well if you have
it. Okay. So then I guess going back to
your career, I mean you worked for 25
years. Is there any notable period of
growth for you during your career and
what do you think drove that growth?
>> Sure. I I think I think the most
cherished time of my career was when I
was working from like a senior software
engineer all the way up to a a senior
enterprise architect. Right. So go going
from from coding to like just designing
and integrating and working with
different applications. Um I felt that I
learned the most about the craft during
that period of time. And what sort of
really helped me a lot was having a
series of extremely
good, knowledgeable, capable mentors
that sort of helped me and taught and
and and kind of guided me to the to the
right path, if you will. Right after I
became a director, the nature of the
work became more um well, it became more
sort of like managerial in a way.
managerial in terms of it was more
helping tech leads, helping other
architects do their jobs. It was more of
selling work to um to seuite executives
all the time and that just became less
fun and there was less growth in my
opinion.
>> You mentioned mentoring being big part
of your career growth. Is there a number
one lesson that you learned from a
mentor and if so what was it? So there
were a lot of a lot of good lessons
taught to me by several quite a few
mentors, right? But if I were to say
that there was one lesson that kind of
stuck by me, it was from this one guy.
He taught he said something that was
kind of profound to me, right? But but
I'll I'll repeat it for everyone. It's
to be flexible. You have to be able to
adapt yourself to changing conditions.
No matter what the condition is, right?
No matter what's your technology stack,
whatever is your CI/CD pipeline,
whatever the client side teams are like,
you just have to stay flexible. If you
can stay flexible, you'll survive. I
remember in one of your videos you
talked about
as you got older and you were working on
tech, the ability to be flexible you
were noticing was becoming harder. It
was harder to stay on top of the trends,
harder to learn. At what ages did you
really notice things were changing for
you? After I turned 40,
I still tried to keep up in the tech and
I still tried to learn all the
frameworks and I just noticed that it
took me longer and longer and longer to
learn. Um, and I know other people have
different sort of experiences, right?
Some people are like in their 50s and
they're still learning quickly, but for
me it just this slowdown became so
incredibly apparent. Um, and it's
in a way it's a little bit it's a little
bit sad in a way. The only way I can
describe it is like imagine like an
Olympic gymnasts like those guys that
can do somersaults in the air, right?
And they're able to do that in their
20s, right? But when they hit their 30s,
if they even try one thing, they'll
break a bone. At least to me, mentally,
that was what it was like. like, hey,
you know, I can learn this framework in
my 20s in like a few days and be
effective with it. In my 40s, it's
taking me weeks to learn it and and what
I can produce is this halting clumsy
syntax that that I probably need to get,
you know, an AI tool to help me polish.
That that gets me a little bit, but it's
life. You know what? We all get older.
when you think about moving forward in
your career and this is right after you
were laid off. Why put out YouTube
videos?
>> Okay, so this is really funny. I I'll
show you this. So, I was in this headsp
space where I was feeling really
confused and lost and it was either
writing my thoughts onto this book here
or shooting a a vlog. And quite frankly,
I was just lazy. I was just lazy. I'm
like, you know what? Why don't I just do
a vlog instead? Because it it was
suggested, I see a I see a therapist,
right? And then she suggested, hey, you
know, you have all of these thoughts
right now and you have anxiety. You have
all this thing. Why not just log it? And
so, it was simply easier to turn on a
camera than it was to spend all this
time writing the words down onto a book.
That's why I did it. Had no clue it
would go viral like the way it did, but
uh that's how things play out. What did
you think when after you put it out and
it was going viral? What were you
thinking and compared to your
expectations?
>> Um, completely blew me away. I I had I
have never I had never done a vlog in my
life, right? And I didn't quite
understand just how the YouTube
algorithm worked to uh to show that vlog
to so many people. It was kind of
surprising and shocking, right? um got a
lot of positive comments from a lot of
people in the video. So, it seemed like
maybe other people were thinking and
feeling similar thoughts and feelings as
to me. And so, so it was it was good. It
was actually kind of therapeutic
to see that I wasn't alone in all of
this.
>> I know you go under the pseudonym of
Asian dad energy, but that video went so
viral and your face is on it. I'm
curious, did anyone where you ever
you're walking around see you and go,
"Hey, you're I saw you on YouTube." Has
that happened yet?
>> So, quite a few co-workers both from my
ex big tech employer and also from my
past uh companies did recognize me and
reach out to me. It was it was pretty
cool. I haven't I haven't yet had
someone reach out to me disapprovingly,
right? I'm sure that will happen at some
point. Maybe a seauite leader would see
this and and like hey man what the heck
are you saying? I'm prepared for those
cringey moments as they come. But so far
it's been all positive.
>> That's awesome. Where do you see this
going from now? What's the future look
like of your career of the YouTube
channel and all of that?
>> I don't know man. The future is
unwritten at this point. I I tried after
right after I got laid off I tried um
applying to a few big tech companies.
Um, not much came of it. Doesn't doesn't
seem like it's a very hot jobs market at
the moment. Um, and also I'm just sort
of thinking about what it is I want to
do, right? I I really I really don't
think at the moment I want to get back
to that structure of big tech where you
have all these schedules and goals and
priorities that that probably doesn't
mean that much to me as it used to. Um,
I'm more thinking, you know, number one,
let me see if I can get used to this
semi early retirement
where I have plenty of time to spend
with people I care about. And by the
way, I don't know if you plan on
retiring early at some point. Um, it's
been pretty good. like it it's been over
a month and and progressively over time
I find my both my physical health and
also my mental sort of uh state of mood
just going up and up and up this whole
time it it's actually been pretty good.
So that's one thing I want to explore
more of this whole semi early retirement
or involuntary early retirement that I
find myself in. The other thing is just
to keep my mind active. I have started a
couple of different projects, right? One
of them is this YouTube channel, Asian
Dad Energy. People seem to like my rants
for whatever reason. So, I'll just do
some more rants as I feel like it. Um,
maybe it's entertaining, maybe people
can find value in it. The other thing is
I've been coding on my own and working
on a couple of small projects. I might I
might put it out there in the world and
see how that does as well. And then
we'll just see where life takes me. I
mean, for for all we know, there could
be some incredibly motivating project
that, you know, I would jump up and work
at it for free. Uh, but I haven't seen
it yet, so we'll do we we'll deal with
the situation as it comes. I one thing I
noticed in your videos and also I mean
in your career story you talked about
you had to sell to the seauite of these
clients when you were a consultant and
um clearly you speak well. If you had to
give advice to a software engineer to
improve on speaking what would you say
is the most important things to get
right?
>> Oh my goodness. It's hard to say. I I
would say just relax and don't don't
associate yourself with the subject that
you're discussing. Right? A lot of times
I see people getting nervous because
they're so invested in what they're
doing. There was actually it's a
interesting story. There was this one
engineer that I worked with
[sighs and gasps] absolutely brilliant
so incredibly brilliant that you have
never met such a smart guy. Okay? But he
couldn't articulate what he was doing
meaningfully to people who weren't
necessarily very deep technically. And
it was so agonizing
when I when I worked with him because
like man you you're a genius man. You
just have to communicate this wisdom to
the people there. But he couldn't do it
because he thought so seriously of what
he was discussing. This was actually a
uh it was actually an in-memory
optimization of a kind of a memory cache
in a CMS system called Drupal. But it
was so he was so tied himself was tied
to this subject that he can't take a
step back and just realize hey don't
take it so seriously and you can discuss
it in a way that's so simple that
everybody can get it and that way you'll
actually get your point across and get
what you want to do. I think that's a
very common failure mode for engineers
is they they speak in the way that they
think but not necessarily in the way
that the audience would want to receive
it. So you're talking to someone who has
no idea on all the super deep uh detail
of the thing that you've just spent
weeks on. You shouldn't get that deep
the way that you're thinking about it.
It's like it's your it's your baby. It's
your everything. But you got to take a
step back and explain it like the
audience is five years old. That that's
in my opinion the best way to do it.
>> Okay. And then yeah, last question I
want to ask you is if you could go back
to the beginning of your career, right,
when you just entered the industry and
give yourself some advice, what would
you say?
>> I I think I would tell myself to work
hard, don't stop learning,
and stay flexible.
>> Awesome. All right. Well, thank you so
much for your time.
>> You're very welcome. It was a pleasure
chatting with you, Ryan.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype. So, I'd love
to show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market. So,
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback for me about the show, I'd love
to hear it. Comments on YouTube have led
to guests coming on like Ilia Gregoric
and David Fowler. I wasn't aware of them
until someone dropped a comment. Also,
feedback in the comments helped me learn
to reduce the number of cliffhers in the
intros. So, your comments definitely
make a difference. Please keep letting
me know what you'd like to see more of
in the show, and I'll see you in the
next episode.